So, hello and welcome to the Wasabi
Wallet Research Club. Uh today we are
speaking from with Sameer from Spyro, uh
which is the title of a fancy
cryptography paper of homomorphic value
encryption or homomorphic encryption and
and private information retrieval. The
the gist of of this crypto magic is that
a client can request data from a server.
So, but the server does not know which
data was requested. Uh and uh there are
different variants of the crypto magic
for different use cases.
And there are currently two
proof-of-concept apps. One is a
Wikipedia.
Uh so, where I think 6 GB of text
entries, no pictures,
uh can be queried so that the server
doesn't know which article you're
interested in.
And the second, more pressing and and
important for us, is an anonymous block
explorer so that you can query the UTXO
set.
Uh
and and request an address and the
server will give you the the balance of
that address.
And well, the the server doesn't know
which address you're actually
requesting. So, that sounds like
impossible magic.
And Sameer, if if the please tell us uh
tell us how how the magic works.
Yeah, that's That was a great
introduction. Honestly, a little better
than the one I had.
Uh thank you. Yeah, um that's exactly
what it is. That's kind of what got me
into this field is that it does sound
like magic and it does sound like you
you probably shouldn't be able to do
something like that. Uh but you can. So,
so yeah. Um I I'm actually going to just
mostly uh I'm
I'll talk a little bit about the
internals of like how Spyro works at the
at the end, but I'll I'll kind of first
just like let's just try to situate
you know, the security model
of a server that doesn't learn what you
query is is kind of complicated. And so,
let's just first try to compare it to
all the other ways you could check a a
Bitcoin balance. And let's just like
situate it amongst the many many
alternative ways, you know, one could
look up the balance of a of a Bitcoin
address.
Um a little background on me, I'm a I I
was a graduate student at Stanford um
and this this PAR project was kind of my
senior project
for my masters and it was advised by Dan
Boneh. But it kind of
I I went and got a real job and so I
stopped working on it for a little bit
and then the the if kind of came back
and I I worked on this again and
published this paper I believe. Yeah, I
guess I presented it in May of this
year. So, um we're starting a company.
I'm I'm quitting my job soon.
So, um yeah. Yeah. And we're trying to
start a company around this technology.
So.
All right. So, um today, you know, I
think we you you guys and and me
probably have a very similar goal, which
is what we want our our private light
clients. We want clients that don't have
to run a full node, but also do not leak
information to third parties or as
little information as possible.
Um today,
uh third parties learn a lot of
information
uh when you use them directly. So, if
you're a light client and you just over
the regular internet
connect to a full node, you are going to
tell them a lot of information. In
particular, they're going to get both
your IP address and your actual, you
know, Bitcoin wallet addresses as you
query them. So, uh that's pretty bad,
you know, you're kind of linking this
this very identity correlated feature,
an IP address, with with your money. Um
You can use a public block explorer to
do this instead of connecting to a full
node directly, but it's it's kind of the
same picture. Uh you're still sending
your IP address and your wallet address
to a third party um who can link them.
A really I really
good frontline solution is to use Tor.
So, a very simple thing to do is to, you
know, remove this network level
identifier, the IP address, um from the
information that the public block
explorer has.
Um there is still kind of like some
leakage, and in particular, the leakage
is going to come from the fact that, you
know, you you typically query many more
than than one address.
And um even using something like Tor,
even if you actually build a new circuit
every time, even if you um
appear to the public block explorer like
someone coming from many different
clients,
uh you're going to still kind of leak
actually the meta metadata, if you will,
that, you know, you're querying on these
addresses at the same time and over Tor.
So,
uh we we kind of have to it's it depends
on the actual practical circumstances,
but there's still even just timing will
leak actually
that these addresses are related. Um and
of course, like figuring out that
addresses are related is actually a
pretty big deal because some of the
point of like things like CoinJoin is to
actually hide that exact information
that that two addresses are controlled
by the same person. So, um
this linkability problem is is is
important, we think.
There's another solution uh in BIPs 157
and 158, uh I think it was implemented
by the Neutrino wallet also, which is
this block filter solution. So,
basically, what happens here,
I'm sure you guys know, but um is
basically compact data about the
transactions in each block is kind of
streamed to the client continuously. And
then when the client sees that a block
contains a relevant transaction, it just
fetches the full block. Um So there's
like a couple complications with this
way of doing things.
One I guess practical thing is that
the blocks are kind of big. The blocks
are 1 MB up to 1 MB each. And and for
for kind of privacy reasons, you can't
just get a subset of the block. So
um if you are if you have a wallet
that's kind of busy, like if if you use
your wallet say every hour, you're you
have to download a megabyte an hour. So
it's it's as frequently as as your
addresses are making transactions,
that's that's how much data you need to
kind of stream.
Um the filters themselves are also, you
know, a kind of continuous ongoing cost
cuz you got to monitor.
So if you're if you offline for some
time, you need to kind of scan through
all the filters and see who were
offline.
And then maybe
uh maybe in a different way, there's
there's kind of this leakage problem. So
um
one problem is we we the act of fetching
the block is not protected. I mean, we
we we announce which block we're we're
trying to fetch. But what we do is I
mean, as a mitigation, you know, if we
if we install with the same node, that
would be bad because the node could kind
of pretty easily tell from the blocks
that you fetch which address you're
interested in. You could just kind of do
an intersection attack. It
can work quite well. Um the mitigation
is generally that you connect to
different peers for each block. So you
connect to a different uh peer to
download each block. But um you know,
again here, the timing really trips us
up, right? Again, just knowing that uh
just just watching
even if I'm not like even if I'm not a
tour adversary, I'm not able to like,
you know, deanonymize you on tour. If
I'm just like your your university
network administrator, and I just watch
your bandwidth consumption, I will just
notice a 1 MB download on some cadence,
right? And if I just like kind of
correlate that with with blocks on the
chain, then I just kind of see, okay, it
seems like you might have downloaded
block 3 and 9 and 9 and 24.
It doesn't become terribly difficult to
figure out an address. So, there's some
leakage. I think in all of these
examples, the attack I outlined is is
kind of theoretical, but it's mostly
just to illustrate that there is leakage
that's still that's still kind of there.
Um, there are some other options which
people kind of suggest. I don't know if
you guys are the audience who would
exactly suggest this. I guess industry
kind of more, I don't know, the A16Z
folks or whatever would say, "Oh, why
don't you just run it on AWS?" But, of
course,
kind of just replacing a box with a
different box, right? Here, now you're
just trusting the cloud provider kind of
to do everything.
And I guess another suggestion folks
have is is running a full node. And I
think that, you know, to be honest, that
is a great suggestion. If you if you if
you
if you want really sovereign kind of
control over the data, I I think a full
running a full node yourself is a good
idea. It is just kind of hard. I mean,
you have to make it remotely accessible.
It's kind of annoying to set up and
maintain.
If we could find a way
without having to run a full node, allow
clients to kind of privately query the
blockchain, that would still be a good
thing because we want to reduce the
barrier to entry. We want more people to
to use this.
Um, yeah, I mean, there aren't that many
full nodes. So, so not that people
do something like this.
So, um the way Spiral works is it uses
homomorphic encryption to remove the
wallet addresses piece of the query. So,
the server is still learning your IP
address, but now there's no useful data
to correlate with that IP address.
Um
the basic idea is uh
Spiral uses homomorphic encryption to
encrypt your query when it leaves your
device, and then it's able to kind of
process your query
and return an encrypted answer
without
um
learning anything about your query.
And the guarantee is it's not it's not
statistical. This is not like a mixing
or or any kind of thing like that. This
is it's not like hashing, it's not
buckets. It's it's a full cryptographic
guarantee that the server cannot learn
anything about the query. So,
um even if they're actively malicious.
Um it does incur higher computational
cost for the server. In particular, the
server has to do work that's linear in
the size of the database. So, if the
database gets bigger, so so today the
database is
uh a bunch of Bitcoin balances. If we
wanted to include, you know, when we
when we added transaction data or if we
want to include more data say about
individual transactions, that will make
the server's runtime longer.
Um but, you know, on the other hand, the
communication is is is better and
there's kind of no ongoing
uh syncing really needed. The server can
kind of keep its database up to date,
and then whenever the client wants to
get the most up-to-date information,
they can make another query.
Um today we only support balances and
the five most recent UTXOs, and that's
because of this thing I talked about
earlier where the computational cost for
the server is linear in the size of the
database. So, if we wanted to make it 10
most recent, it it cost more. Um so, we
we need to think carefully about
how we can make that kind of scale to at
least a use case that's that's useful.
And uh yeah, of course the code is open
source and there's a paper and
everything and I'm I'm happy to answer
any questions about about how it works.
I have a slide that kind of explains
more of the technical underpinnings of
of spiral. So, if you want, I can I can
just go through that slide. If you want
to hear more about homomorphic
encryption stuff. Uh but before I do
that, I'll just kind of say, yeah, I
think the open questions for us are
you know, what what minimum set of data
is enough? I think balance is is on its
own is it's not quite enough. I think if
I was
when I run a wallet software, I kind of
expect more than just the balance and
all my in all my addresses.
Um, we obviously need to think about
fetching more than one address. Today,
there's like a website and you can fetch
one address, but
you know, wallets have more than one
address. And
um
yeah, I think there's a couple options
on how we do that. Um, we need to think
a little bit about the pay or
incentivization structure for servers.
This is a kind of costly computation, so
how can we um make it feasible or
practical for them? And um long term, I
I think I would like to see an open
standard for PIR for this data. So, what
we want is something that's not tied to
a company or or a person or or an
organization, but it's kind of ideally
like maybe a bit or something that um
uh allows us to not tie ourselves to any
particular scheme and and do this PIR
thing um
as an extension of our current way of,
you know, say doing an get block RPC or
whatever.
So, yeah.
Um, would you like me to to to just go
through the homomorphic encryption step
cuz I got I got I got the
Would that be interesting? Yeah, go.
Mhm. Uh Max actually maybe we can take
an intermission just to ask a few
questions and then we'll continue Sure,
that sounds great. Yeah.
Um because I think a lot of people are
going to have questions here and uh
um
I'll just start myself. Can Can you kind
of give us a ballpark of the the cost
of the server of the UTXO?
Sure. So So
I guess today what we do is we take the
UTXO set and we kind of
summarize So today we take the UTXO set
and for every address we take the top
five UTXOs if there are up to five and
we also compute its balance and that's
the data we we we do today.
Um if if you wanted to say query the
entire UTXO set, that would be slightly
bigger than than what I outlined but not
not that much bigger.
Um
if you want a sense of the the size of
the computational cost, maybe the
simplest summary would be
you know, for every
uh
Yeah, I guess uh
if you think of the database size
the computational cost is is is about
300 megabytes per second.
So what that means is like if the
database is 1 gig, it takes three CPU
seconds to do this task.
So um
the task is fully parallelizable so you
can think of computation as just a cost,
you know, like if you if you did it with
three cores, you know, you would take 1
second
uh but yeah, it's it's around 300
megabytes per second.
I see. Um so the big situation here is
that for Wasabi wallet um we would want
as like like an MVP for us to work.
The the amounts simply wouldn't be
enough.
Our users, they want proof. They want to
know that it's connected
to block headers that are in the chain
with the most proof of work.
But on top of that, we also need to know
that the server isn't in some ways
deceiving us.
For example, just lowering the balances
of all the users or just omitting
certain UTXOs.
Block filters do a nice job of of this
because
you're you know, you're just hoping the
server does an accurate job of creating
the filters and you're querying the
blocks and you get these entire blocks.
So, you know, the only way that you're
going to have an incorrect balance is if
the server somehow malleates a filter,
but there's not really a good
you know, it's kind of a weird
unclear
attack vector. So, so how how practical
would it be to actually get some kind of
proofs on top on top of the balance that
that you're already producing? Yeah,
yeah, that's a great question. So, so so
Um,
I'm forgetting
the the exact name of this is So, so
what we want is a Merkle inclusion
proof, right? We we we just want to say
that this transaction is part of this
block and to do that we need the log if
and it's the number of transactions. We
need like log n kind of hashes to show
inclusion.
Um, I think we used this kind of Merkle
proof of inclusion somewhere else, but
I'm forgetting. Um, I think there's a
wallet that that uses these. Um,
but
Yeah, so to those that that would be
more costly and and yeah, to be here
today, we definitely do not have any
kind of like, you know, there's no proof
server is is really serving you the
right data. So, so that is a big
problem. Obviously, we need to kind of
have some proof. Uh the good news is,
yeah, we we could always add Merkle
proofs of inclusion. If you If you do
the math on the size of those, you know,
it's like roughly I think I looked at
this before. It was like something like
on the order of hundreds of bytes, like
maybe 200 bytes or something. Uh so, it
would be a significant increase, but uh
possible. I I'll I'll highlight one
alternative way of doing this, which is
actually suggested in the BIP
uh 157.
Uh
There uh what we could instead do is
actually continue to use
uh block filters, but use PIR for the
block retrieval part.
So, you would you would retrieve blocks
using PIR, uh but you would use client
block filters as normal. I think the
problem there is it doesn't save any
bandwidth. I mean, I I
could be wrong, but I I think most of
bandwidth is coming from the filters and
coming from the streaming to the client
of the filter data.
Uh so, you wouldn't save that.
Just as a
Yeah, just as a heads-up for you, we're
downloading the the filters from our
server, like the Wasabi backend server,
but then the blocks are downloaded from
the Bitcoin peer-to-peer network. So,
the server doesn't incur the block
download cost.
Oh, okay. So, is the main cost for you
guys right now actually the filters
because you incur that cost? As I see.
Yeah, it's a large outgoing cost. I'm
sure your hosting provider is
is charging you.
Uh
Yeah. Okay. Yeah, so so um yeah,
actually doing proofs of inclusion is is
possible, but uh yeah, it's good to
know, yeah, you you need that kind of to
deploy this for real.
Um I What I'm I If I can ask a follow-up
question, do you do you guys do you guys
to do this? Do you are you mostly
querying the UTXO set, the full set of
transactions,
just balances? Like what kind of data is
is is crucial?
Uh, we do want the full transaction
history list.
And and
so that's what we have in the filters
right now. Wasabi is SegWit only, so we
don't have to create filters pre-SegWit
August 2018 or something or 17. Um,
yeah.
And the filters are as large as the
number of
back 32 addresses in the blocks.
Sorry, say that one more time. The the
filters are all essentially a compact
representation of all
back 32 addresses in a block.
Single public key. Okay, yeah. Mhm.
Single public key back 32 addresses. So,
um, they're very compact,
you know, 3 years ago because it was a
a minority of people used those
addresses.
More and more
they become larger and larger, but
they're they're they're very space
efficient.
I would
I don't know the exact details. Maybe
Max can answer, but the exact
700 megabytes or something. I think it's
below a gigabyte on my field here, but
it's it's not that much.
Oh, below a gigabyte for the entire 4
years.
That might be complete [__] but I
think yes.
That sounds right. I mean, it's it's not
that much data, right? It's it's a
because it it's also statistical, right?
It's a bloom filter-esque thing, right?
It's a That's right.
When it's not exact,
then there are some false positives, but
there are no
false negatives. That's the goal. You'll
never
but you will get blocked.
Yeah, but that false negative that false
positive rate can be configured and the
lower you want that false positive rate,
the larger the filter size is.
I'm not exactly sure where we fall in
the line of of trade-off here.
Um yeah, I I don't know details like
that. Lucas is in the call, so maybe he
knows.
Happy to take any other questions, also.
Uh hello guys. Um it was quite nice to
be here. Uh
I I don't have any back um strong
background in crypto and uh higher order
math, but um
as a layman, uh
you know,
is
is there a way to um simplify the
explanation of how homomorphic
encryption works? Uh
I have tried to see the
you know, the information on the
internet, but uh it's just not um
possible for a um
basic uh
you know, a layman like me. Would Would
that be possible in this call or is it
not?
Yeah, I I have a slide. Um let's let's
talk a little bit more about Wasabi
Wallet and and privacy, but then I I
will I will I can give that explanation.
Does that Does that sound good?
Yes, thank you very much. Uh yeah, thank
you.
Yeah, but what I do wonder is um you you
do need to know the inputs um like the
the value of the UTXO that you're trying
to spend. Uh does does your database
include amounts?
Yes.
Yeah. Yes.
Um so so the total size of our database
is is roughly 1 gig right now. Um we we
we translate every all UTXOs kind of
reduced down to about a gig of data.
Um, if we instead made the set all UTXOs
and we didn't just take the five most
recent ones for every address. Um,
yeah, the database would not be much
larger. It'd be like a small multiple,
like maybe three or four times larger.
That would be kind of feasible. I guess
when I'm
uh
thinking about it is I suppose it it
helps that you guys only support the the
back 32 addresses cuz that means um
there's kind of a limited set of
addresses that are on chain that have
transactions for that, but
um
yeah, we need to think about
how big would it be to include all
transaction history cuz cuz UTXOs are
very different than, you know, every
transaction.
So, um
yeah, okay. It's good to know what what
the yeah. And and the just to just to
ask one more time. So, the so the the
problem that you guys face with block
filters is
mostly that you have to download this
this gigabyte of of things to get
started. Is that the issue mostly?
So, you have to download First of all,
the server has to generate filters,
which can take weeks.
Um, then the the the clients have to
download all the filters, which we do
over Tor,
um which also takes can take, well, an
hour maybe.
But then we have a lot of
it's all over Tor. So, so that also
Exactly. Yeah. Yes, and then and for
block downloads, we spin up a new Tor
identity for every Bitcoin peer that we
download a block from.
Uh so, all of this together is if you
have a really big wallet and you're
making a full rescan, I mean, it can
take a couple weeks if not a month.
I see the issue. Yeah, so so there
Yeah, weeks if not a month, man. Okay,
so
Hm. Let me just add one more So, what
when you use Wasabi Wallet, you're
making many addresses.
Um
uh because you're you're coinjoining, so
you have to make a new address every
time. And um if you use the wallet
regularly, you might go through
something like 300 addresses or 400 or
1,000. Um
over time, that means that what you're
looking for in the filters is actually
quite broad. Right. Um and so you get
more and more false positives. Um
and so if you if you just if you just
think it through, you're going to have,
you know, 1,000 blocks or more. And each
block is actually more than a megabyte
typically. Um and so you might end up
with
a gigabyte of of blocks that you have to
query, and each one is queried from a
different uh node over a different Tor
circuit.
Not necessarily different node, just a
different Tor circuit.
Mhm. So so I guess there are two things
to ask you. One is So so one thing to
notice, you know, it's perfectly fine to
use this homomorphic stuff with Tor, you
know, like they're kind of orthogonal.
Um one kind of hides your IP and one
hides the content of your queries. Doing
both is is probably a good thing. Um but
I wonder if what what homomorphic
encryption could allow you to do is not
construct a new circuit like every time.
So the So if if the query is encrypted,
in a sense you don't need to use Tor,
but if you if you'd like to also kind of
hide your network level identifier, you
could do both and
use Tor, but not build a new circuit
every time, and instead make many
private queries to the same to the same
node.
Um
this would be presumably faster because
Tor circuits can can reach decent
bandwidth, right? But not if they're I
think freshly constructed every time,
right? Then you're going to pay the
latency.
Can we actually make batch requests with
Sparrow? Like requesting multiple
addresses simultaneously?
Yeah, yeah.
So so if you notice today, no, right? I
mean, we just have like a text field
with with it with an address.
Um
We we want to support that. There's
there's actually a lot of theory and
research about about
doing batch requests kind of more
efficiently.
Um so
yeah, I think I think
uh
it's really useful to hear that a very
typical use case is like hundreds of
addresses. Cuz that says a lot about
how we need to build this to make it
usable, you know? Um
So yeah, okay.
Yes, um so so batching is possible. It's
it's
but it's in the works. Yeah.
Yeah, by the way, it's it's way more
than just a thousand. I'm checking a
not even that old wallet
and it has well, 8,000 addresses.
Here is the 13,000 addresses. Wow.
we do
you know, we do we attempt many
coinjoins and a lot of them fail and we
generate new addresses for each
attempted coinjoin
and you can register up to eight outputs
in a in a round. So
let's say a round fails, I don't know,
five times before it succeeds. So that's
five times eight addresses
um that that
we we have to add to your gap limit.
I see.
So so are the are the addresses that you
that you create there? Do they are they
unspent? Are they do they contain any I
mean, if you if you create an address
and no one hears about it, did it did it
really get created?
Well well, in this case, yes, because
the coinjoin coordinator hears about it
and probably also the other coinjoin
signers. So, it's semi-public-ish.
Yes, but did it never did will it store
value? It will, right? I guess to start
the coinjoin it it had to have some some
value in it. Yeah. Uh no, sorry. So, we
spend inputs that that are addresses
with money on them, but then on the
output side we create new addresses that
are not yet used without money on it.
Oh, I see. So, they they empty output
addresses.
Exactly. Those are addresses that never
were on the blockchain in an output with
any amount of sats. It's just
unused addresses so to say. Mhm. So,
then does it not need to actually hit
any kind of the
We don't need to query the blockchain
for them at all, right?
Well the client doesn't know if an
address is empty or not. So, we need to
query all of them. Just a lot of them
the server will say there's nothing on
here.
I see. I see.
Yeah, so an easy way to actually resolve
that will be to actually just make a set
of addresses that have any money.
So so, you know,
this is a technique we actually use for
the
for the current service. What you can do
is instead create another database that
just says like, does this address have
any money at all?
Um Uh-huh. And uh that that database can
be can be very small, right? Because
again, we can use like the classic Bloom
filter thing where we It's not quite a
Bloom filter cuz the addresses are
already random. So, just take the X top
top X bits of every address that
uh
has money in it. And send these to the
client or allow them to fetch them using
PIR, right? So, um
Yeah.
And wasabi wallet already handles the
mempool, right? Um, you guys already
like kind of privately listen to
everything on the mempool and and then
cross reference it with the addresses
you have and all and all that. So. Yeah,
we build a local mempool. The issue is
when we're offline, we of course don't
know it. So maybe actually some private
information that we will go over someone
else's mempool might be another
interesting use case.
Mhm.
Yeah, so.
Um, so sorry, a bit more about the batch
requests. So like would it be possible
to just send 10,000 addresses
uh to this to the server and he responds
in a single uh
package?
So it's definitely possible. I mean, the
simpler way is yeah, you can send 10,000
queries, you can upload them all and
then just kind of the server can just do
all the computation and send you all the
responses. The problem is going to be
well, the problem is going to be
twofold. One,
there's a significant cost to
to running a query. So a query costs
today like six CPU seconds, right? So
six CPU seconds, it's not nothing, but
it's also it's something, you know, like
it's it's uh it's a significant cost. So
so 10,000 addresses times
six CPU seconds is 60,000, it's you
know, 1,000 hours of computation.
Uh so
it'll be tough. Uh so what in order to
to make that work, to make 10,000
addresses work, what we need is to is to
do
batching or reduce the number of
addresses that we're effectively
querying by, you know, like I said, like
figuring out whether the addresses are
empty or
um you know, kind of reducing the set
that way. Um, but yeah, 10,000 is is
hard. Um,
Uh, the other thing is going to the
other problem is to be communication.
So, like every query is is is 14
kilobytes. So, 10,000 * 14 kilobytes is,
you know,
a lot. And then, uh, that's a lot of 140
megabytes to upload.
So, it's it's Yeah, it's not going to be
that feasible.
Um,
yeah.
Yeah.
Actually, to this I have a question
because I I saw on the website that the
first request the client needs to send
more data and for every following it's
less. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, it's because,
um, the the first request, uh, contains
what's called like
the setup data or the public parameters.
Basically, the server sends
essentially like an extended like a
large public key to the server. So, the
server uses this this public key to kind
of, uh,
let it do the the query processing.
Um,
so, it's it's, uh,
it's state that the server needs to
store on a per client basis, but it's
not, uh,
it has no privacy implication. It's
just, uh, used for the homomorphic
processing. Yeah.
Mhm.
So, that's why it's big. And it Yeah,
you you might have noticed it's pretty
big. It's like 8 megabytes or something.
So.
And does that size depend on the
database size?
It does not. Or it it, uh, extremely It
only logarithmically does. So, it's like
very it's I mean, like if the database
was 100 times bigger, it would be like
12 megabytes or something.
Mhm.
Yeah, like
I mean, mhm.
To just general like
it's a very broad question, but is it
So, if we want to have the the full TX
offset of all like of
Oh, but actually now we probably also
want transaction IDs and stuff like
this. So, basically we want the full
transaction metadata blockchain thing
for all segwit and taproot outputs.
Yeah.
And let's say we have I don't know
10,000 users or so and each of them has
let's say 1,000 addresses or so. Mhm.
Mhm. Like you know I I
and this is still rather small scale,
but is
Yeah. Like is this completely crazy or
is it something like that?
no no. You you're asking a very a very
good question. So, so I think that the
way that it's not So, so that's that's
very true. So, so I think like
it is difficult especially from a cost
perspective I think for the for the
server. It's difficult to see this
scaling to
I check 10,000 addresses kind of
regularly. Like every you know, every
day I check 10,000 addresses and there's
like 10,000 users. You know, that that
will quickly become difficult for the
server.
But
I think there's two things. One is
the set of active addresses is not
10,000. So, what can we do to kind of
like
reduce the number.
Two
it is just a cost for the server. You
know, computation is just money as we as
we know from proof of work, right? So,
a question is, you know, if clients were
willing to pay for it, if I was willing
to pay for six CPU seconds for my query,
maybe that would be okay. I might not be
willing to pay 10,000 * 6
CPU seconds. So, we we'd have to see
what clients are kind of you know, quote
and quote willing to pay. Um
and then also I I guess the last thing I
would say is it is it would be very
feasible to use PAR just for blocks.
So, if you think that the privacy
leakage is an issue or you're interested
in in that kind of angle on it, I think
just doing PIR just just in that block
retrieval phase of the standard
client block header thing, if you want
to do PIR, I think that is is is very
very feasible.
One one one other thing um
I think that uh
there's kind of like a
there's also like a kind of narrow use
case for just like onboarding
or or just like setup. I think if you're
like a client who's setting up and it's
taking weeks to sync your wallet, I
think it's really powerful that in the
meantime you can
you can make queries
uh for for addresses. You can see if
you've been paid
um privately.
Yeah, exactly, right? So, just get the
active wallet balance really quickly and
Yeah, so no syncing, no
So, so actually it might it might even
make sense just as a kind of
Yeah, as a fallback or even kind of as a
like setup thing. I mean, the fact that
you don't incrementally have to do
anything. Like each query costs the same
and or I guess the first one costs a
little more, but but basically there's
no syncing, right? There's no like
client state that I'm trying to get into
sync with the chain. I I'm just kind of
I can make a query kind of one-off.
Something I noticed is can you query the
balance of an address that's not in your
wallet today? I I think you can add a
public watch address, but you can't you
can't actually use it like a block
explorer, right?
Yeah, you cannot. And the problem is you
would have to run this address through
all the filters, download all the past
false positive blocks. And so, it would
take a long time.
Yeah, I don't know if it's a feature you
guys are interested in, but I I think it
would be useful to be able to just say,
"Hey, what uh you know, like yeah, how
much is that this address?" Cuz today,
you know, the option is to go to a
Chrome tab and type it in and like send
it to you know, who knows. Um send it to
blockchain.com or whoever.
Mhm. Yeah, and by the way, um if you
receive a transaction and you want to
uh
then you don't know the inputs of that
transaction. So,
you
or sorry, the input amount of that
transaction, because that's on the
blockchain, not in the transaction
itself, right? It's on the previous
transaction output.
Um and and then you cannot do effective
fee bumping in a child pays for parent
transaction.
Uh because you you'd Uh so, this is an
issue that we have of kind of good stuck
payments that you received.
And maybe something like that might be
helpful. And so, you you can query the
amount of that input and then do better
fee bumping.
I see. I see. So, so, so,
to summarize, like you're you you have a
you have a you know you received a
payment, but you just don't know how
much it is essentially, because you that
information is just
kind of not local.
Um no you so, you you receive a
transaction where on the output side
your address is. That's why the
transaction was hit in in the filter,
right?
Uh
but, you don't know the value of the
inputs exactly, right? Because that's in
the previous transaction output. So, you
don't know the the fee rate that this
current transaction has. Oh, you know
what that's not equal to, but you don't
you don't know
uh what what gap was left for the miner
in in the form of a fee. I see. Exactly.
And then you can do child pays for
parent fee calculations.
Yeah, so that is a yeah, that is
It's just one of those edge cases where
we thought it would be nice to be able
to just well, search for an address.
Yeah.
But then we realized yeah, it will take
minutes, you know,
hours.
Right. I think
I think it yeah, so so long-term I guess
I have a slide on this, but
um
Oh, no. Um I think long-term
we would like to build a like an SDK so
that we're not kind of like individually
hand engineering the homomorphic
encryption, but so that it's kind of a
totally generic thing. So so the dream
is that there's like
a piece of code that you point a bunch
of like basically an array at and then
there's an endpoint that you can
privately query that data using. So
certainly for like all these kinds of
smaller things that you want to do, that
really really kind of makes sense.
Mhm, definitely. Oh, yeah, by the way,
to jump back, so you say the client
needs to upload his homomorphic public
key to the server.
So then all the queries are connected to
the same public key?
So
all of the queries are made using the
same
yes, they're they're each query is
connected to the same let's say key
pair.
Um the the crucial part is that every
query is encrypted. So it's encrypted
under this key. So it's it's not uh
the queries I I guess are identifiably
from the same party, but what the
queries are for is not.
So I guess there's so there you're
you're right, there's some meta metadata
almost that's that's still visible,
right? Cuz you can see I guess the main
leakage is timing. So you can see that
some party made five queries over of
period of time.
I see. So you would want to go extreme
and even hide
this type of meta data then or use a
different public key or or key pair each
time. Yes. Yes. Yes.
more data for every query. Yes.
And then do some randomization in the
timing as well. Plus the core circuits.
And then it gets a lot more inefficient
as well. Yeah.
Yeah. Um some some some some mitigations
for timing are just pacing. So, so a
simple thing you can do is just kind of
like
uh
just pace requests and uh send dummy
requests. Uh but yes, obviously these
incur costs. So, yeah.
Yeah, I mean today if you want to do the
same thing for block filters,
you you you are kind of stuck in that I
mean the timing
alone of your request is going to kind
of correlate them. So, um
yeah.
It is kind of a tough problem.
That's why batch requests are also very
important, I would say.
Yeah. Yeah, certainly a batch request
where we round up the size. So, like uh
it would be important to kind of like
not reveal the exact number of addresses
you have in your wallet just because
that is probably kind of identifiable.
So, uh yeah, if we just if we just round
up the number of addresses and let you
query, you know, up to X thousand
addresses at a time. Uh yeah.
Hm.
I will um
I will do some more research and
thinking on batching. It's very useful.
Thank you so much for like
talking to us and and letting us hear
like your problems and stuff. Um
I think it'll be useful to go back and
look at batching and see if it can be
practical.
Super cool. So, then
let's
like how how long does then the a
request
take? Like so, let's say we want to look
thousand or so.
Mhm. How long does the client have to
wait?
The client has to wait for as long as it
wants to for almost directly in
proportion to how much it's willing to
pay.
So, I mean, uh if you want to make 1,000
1,000 queries, right? Let's say it's
it's uh you know, 5,000 seconds of of
computation, right? Uh if you pay the
server,
uh as you know, computation is like kind
of cheap and parallelizable. So, you can
imagine a server, especially like it
starts to look basically like a cloud
provider or something, that just goes,
"Okay, if you pay me 5,000 times 1 cent
or you know, 0.1 cents or whatever,
I'll I'll process your query in 1 second
cuz I'll just throw 5,000 cores at it."
Uh-huh. So, so it is kind of it is
infinitely divisible. It's it's naively
parallel as an algorithm, so.
That's really interesting to hear.
Mhm.
So, yeah.
there's a nice Yeah.
There's an interesting intersection with
the fact that this is all for a payment
system, right?
So, it would be interesting to think
about Yeah.
Okay, I think I'm pretty much out of
questions for now. Does anyone else have
any?
No, then it would be nice to get a bit
more into the the crypto magic. If you
could get into that.
I I'm uh if if this altitude is is kind
of too much or too little, let me know.
Um
the slide is kind of
kind of gross-looking, but uh I'll I'll
I'll just walk through uh
I'll walk through the basics of how this
works. So, here's how this
kind of works on the inside.
So, so basically, remember we have a
client uh and a server, and we'd like
the client would like to retrieve an
item from this database of items without
letting the server learn which one uh it
queries. So, basically, if we imagine
our indexes is three, like we want the
third item of the database, what we're
going to do is we're going to have the
client create a kind of bit vector. So,
a vector of bits.
Uh if you remember linear algebra, I'm
using the word vector kind of on
purpose. So, it's a, you know, column
vector of bits where it's a one-hot
encoding. If you've been around machine
learning, you might have heard the term
one-hot before, but basically that means
there's a one in the location that I
want to retrieve and zeros everywhere
else. So, there's a zero in these
entries and there's a one
uh at the desired index.
So, I'm going to form this this vector.
It's just a plain text bits on on my
client. And then I'm going to encrypt
each of them.
So, I'll explain, you know, the the
encryption we use has a special
property, um which we'll get to, but
basically it it it is also it behaves
mostly like a normal encryption scheme.
So, you encrypt each bit, and now these,
you know, these encrypted bits get sent
to the server. And just like if you AES
encrypted them, uh the server can't tell
what any of these bits encrypt. I It's
kind of crucial to remember that like
you know, the encryption of zero and the
encryption of zero, they they don't look
the same. Every time you encrypt zero,
you get a different-looking random
thing.
Uh and the server cannot uh kind of
distinguish whether you encrypted the
same thing or a different thing. So,
that So, that property applies. It's
It's called uh chosen plain text
security or or semantic security. But,
basically, yeah, you know, this vector
of encrypted bits, it's not uh visible
to the server which ones are zero or
which ones are one.
So, that gets sent to the server. And
then, how does the server actually
figure out uh the answer to your query?
Well, uh if you you if you You at the
plain text
database elements in green,
it does this kind of special This is the
special property of the encryption.
Um the encrypted zero gets multiplied by
the plain text, you know, eight here.
And what we get is the encrypted product
of them. So, if we multiply encrypted
zero by six, we'll get zero. If we
multiply encrypted one by seven, we'll
get encrypted seven.
So, the the point is this this this
ability to do this multiplication,
that's not normal.
Normal encryption doesn't let you do
that. So, if you AES encrypts zero and
then like multiply by eight, you will
just get garbage. There's no It does not
become like encrypted zero. Um this is
what Sorry. Yeah.
The on on the the left-hand right-hand
side, the number four, E0 * 8 = E0.
Is Is the 2 * E0 is that the exact same
thing or just a different encrypted blob
with the same zeros plain text?
It It is not the exact same thing. So,
do you mean Do you mean on the left and
right? Like this encrypted zero and this
encrypted zero?
Yes.
Yeah. So, so they are not the same
thing.
Um
they actually again to the attacker look
completely indistinguishable and random.
So, they they both look
what they what they encrypt looks
completely uh
hidden to the attacker to to any to the
server.
Nice. Thanks.
Continue, please. So, so then you can
add up You can do the same thing just
like we multiply, you can also you're
allowed to add. So, if you add encrypted
zero and encrypted seven, you get
encrypted seven.
Uh and so on. So, you kind of add all of
the results and now you have a single
encrypted result that you can send back
to the client. The client can decrypt
and get the item that it wanted.
So, this is how it's kind of
let's say possible to do this. Um you
should There's There's probably one
glaring problem with this toy example,
which is that we uploaded in our query
the same number of elements that as are
in the database. So, our query is very
very big, you know. Um so, that that's a
problem. So, so in the real scheme,
there's kind of a whole bunch of
complicated stuff you can do to mitigate
that. Basically, you can kind of
structure the the database as a cube and
kind of send bits that correlate to each
kind of dimension or axis on the cube,
and then you can multiply and reduce
that way. Um and then that makes the
query smaller, you know. So, but uh this
is the gist of it. This is how it works.
So, the point is now you can maybe
conceptualize how if there was an
encryption scheme that did these things,
then you could do PIR, you know. If
there was an encryption scheme that had
this
this multiplication and this addition
operation,
then it would all work.
So, then the question becomes, okay,
well, how do you get an encryption
scheme like that? It's not something
that AES does. It's not something that
even ECC really does. Um
so, um
yeah, the process of getting that is is
is more involved. But, that's the gist
of This is the gist of how how this
scheme works.
Any questions? I'm I I know it's like a
super
it's complicated. I'm happy to answer
anything. I haven't given this talk that
many times, so it's a little
I'm happy to answer anything.
Yeah, that's it's pretty nice. Um the
the data size in number four for the
orange boxes on the right.
So, E0 E0 E7 E0
is
and then underneath the sum of E7 again,
so that the is the data size of these
orange blobs different especially the
sum?
Yeah, it's a great question. So no, so
all the encrypt all the orange blocks
have the exact same size. So
that's a very good point, you know, like
this vector of encrypted zeros and ones
it's it's not small, right? Cuz every
one of them is is big enough to hold
a plain text element. So it's it's it's
pretty big.
There are a bunch of things you can do
to kind of not actually send
uh encrypted zeros and encrypt So
I guess I can I can just I can just
explain it this way. Um
so the operations we have are are
homomorphic multiplication by a plain
text item
and um
like here and addition.
I don't
know your familiarity with like linear
algebra or something, but that's that's
uh that's a not quite complete set.
If if you were also able to multiply two
encrypted numbers
you can kind of do the
you can think about it and and see that
actually you can compute any function on
encrypted data if you have addition and
multiplication. You know, addition and
multiplication kind of
every computation is like a
composition of of adding and
multiplying, right? Our our all our
computers do are add and multiply. So
um
there's a there are there are ways to
kind of
uh compute an arbitrary function on
encrypted data. So what that means is
the the query is now much smaller and
you perform this arbitrary computation
to make all of these encrypted zeros and
ones in a big way while keeping the
query small. So um yeah.
So tomorrow
Okay, and is where I saw this um
illustration
and because
sent me the
the link to it before.
My question is
what is the mathematical principle that
enables this um
I'm I'm I'm a bit familiar with linear
algebra, so that should be
Yeah, so yeah.
Yeah, so the the the the the main
principle is that it's difficult to kind
of
uh
invert matrices when they have noise.
So, I can say more about that, but
basically what that means is like if you
have a matrix, a large random matrix
and you multiply it by a vector
the outputs are are easy to determine.
The output and the input vector are kind
of correlated. It's easy to invert the
matrix and figure out what the input was
from the output. So, if you have AS
uh you know if I give you AS and I give
you
A, it's easy to find S because finding
the inverse of a matrix is not hard.
But the the key insight, the algebraic
insight that like enables this is that
uh well, if I give you AS plus E
where E is just some very small noise
uh suddenly the problem is very hard.
It's very hard to figure out
S from AS plus E.
Um the post has I think like further
down kind of
a discussion of like learning with
errors and stuff.
In in programming we have this
concept of you know in I IEEE floating
numbers there's epsilon. What's that?
Is that related to that E? Like what
No. No, so so it's not like super small
I mean when I say small, I don't mean
like infinitesimally small like epsilon.
I just mean that it's small relative to
the size of the of the of the data.
Yeah, so it's just it's small enough
that when the client decrypts it can
kind of round away the error. So you can
think of it it's less like epsilon more
like like error. Like you know like that
floating point error where you add like
1.0000
1 and 1.000 1 and you get two, you know,
because of that floating point error.
It's it's kind of analogous to that.
It's more like there's kind of this
small error that you can ignore at the
end. Um also to Max's point, I remember
I I forgot to mention something which is
interesting which is you asked whether
this left and right thing are are
different and they are. To the attacker
they're indistinguishable. But something
that isn't happening that is kind of
interesting is that each ciphertext
contains noise. So what's happening
every time we do one of these operations
is the noise inside the ciphertext is
growing.
And when I say noise it's kind of sounds
fuzzy, but but basically there's noise
inside every ciphertext and as you do
operations to it noise grows and when
the noise is too big, uh when you
decrypt you'll get the wrong answer.
You'll get an incorrect decryption and
you won't know it. Um so so so part of
it is that the
there is something happening when you do
these multiplications and these
additions. The noise is growing. You
can't do it an unlimited number of
times. Um otherwise the ciphertext will
kind of become garbage. Oh.
Yeah.
Okay, that's that's uh that's uh the way
you explained it in uh in the terms of
matrices that yeah, I think it's it
clicked something on me.
You know, Yeah, yeah, sure. Yeah.
Yeah, feel free to reach out if you have
other questions, yeah.
Yeah, sure.
Another thing is that how
how do you get this kind of noise? Does
it um
you know, when you deal with the
floating numbers, you know, just a
little bit of noise can throw off
calculations like in the six and stuff.
How is that dealt with with this
encryption scheme?
Yeah, it's a good question. So so we um
Yeah, I mean for the
the the noise we use is sampled from the
Gaussian distribution, so like a normal
distribution.
Um
And what we do is like we kind of before
we run a computation, we kind of almost
like
predict or check ourselves. We check
okay, if we do this computation, what's
going to happen to the noise
distribution? And we kind of calculate
like a a bound.
We calculate the standard deviation of
the noise distribution at the end.
Uh in advance.
And we make sure that, you know,
the
we we make sure that the noise
distribution is is
not so wide as to make the ciphertext
like unreadable as to, you know, like
cause an error in the in the decryption.
So basically what we do is we bound the
standard deviation of the output noise.
And by by doing that, we can we can say,
you know, the noise will always be
within six standard deviations of the
mean and we know the standard deviation
is going to be X and so
we know that
we will decrypt correctly.
Yeah.
Okay, cool.
That's all for me. Thank you so much.
Yeah, no worries.
Hello guys.
Hello. Yeah, Adam. Glad that you're
here.
Catch the recording. It was really good.
Um
I I do have another question and that is
um about the
So what I saw the client on GitHub and
it mentioned that this is free open
source. What about the server?
So the server does not need to be open
source, but because of like homomorphic
encryption guarantees, but I think we
still are open sourcing it. So the
server is at
my GitHub.
Uh it's at this one. I think this is our
old repo. So
I can message it in the chat.
So there is a server here. So So we also
have
uh the server
uh open source and public. I do think
that the
uh
the
the really crucial part is to get kind
of reproducible builds and stuff on the
client cuz the client as long as you
trust the client everything else is is
fine. So um yeah.
But obviously for an open standard we're
going to need
open source clients and servers.
Cool. Thank you.
So I just arrived.
Is there a way to
to to summarize
all Spiral work
in uh
like
like I'm five?
It's magic. Sure. Sure. Sure. Yeah, I
think the summary the best summary is
honestly Max's at the beginning which
was just like basically Spiral is a way
to retrieve an item from a database
without letting it ever learn what item
you retrieved.
And the way it works is kind of
complicated but
But But let let just What does that
mean?
Like
Okay. Okay. I can I can do a little I
can I can explain a little more. So, so,
yeah,
um
the way it works intuitively is
basically the client sends this kind of
encrypted vector of bits
and the server does like a
encrypted dot product between the bits
that the client sends and the items in
the database. And the point is, you
know,
uh the one bit will kind of be the item
that we want and the zero bits will kind
of cancel out all the items we don't
want. And the server will add these all
up and send it back to the client. And
the point is the server never learns,
you know, what the encrypted bits were.
It never learns what the sum of
everything was. Uh it just kind of does
the computation and sends the encrypted
result back to the client. O- okay,
okay. So, it's like a cryptographic
challenge
pro- protocol.
That's uh that's like you the server is
sending bytes, but those bytes are not
the address, but somehow with a
client-server
challenge, you can
you can establish the address or or the
information that the server is sending
On the client
Holy [__] that's Yeah, so that's what
it's basically Yeah, so the client is
sending an encrypted version of its
query and it gets an encrypted response
and the point is the server never
decrypts anything. Yeah, that's the
point. Everything stays encrypted. So,
it's kind of like it's almost like
end-to-end encryption. Like you you send
something out and get it back.
The catch is that it's it's uh expensive
for the server to do the computation.
So, you know, the server has to invest a
lot of effort to kind of answer your
query.
So, you might need to eventually pay
them or like in some way incentivize
their their behavior.
How expensive
is it so expensive
as for the entire Bitcoin transaction
history uh blockchain
wouldn't be able to run on a single
server no matter how big you are trying
to buy?
It's a good question. Uh I mean it used
to be
impossibly big. It used to be like, you
know, I would say years, you know, to do
a single Bitcoin address look up. But um
today it's not so bad. So, today there's
been a lot of innovation. Today you can
look up a balance of an address today at
our site uh like very easily and our our
server costs I think like 50 bucks a
month to run or something. It's not an
expensive server that we run. Uh so,
today it's not too bad. Uh I think doing
all of the transaction history is
definitely more costly, but it's still
not it's not like infeasibly costly. I
think it gets maybe really bad if you
are trying to query, you know, tens of
thousands of addresses. Then we'll have
to think of a better way uh to kind of
batch your your queries.
Yeah, so Adam, there's multiple layers
of why this isn't might be very
difficult for us to use. One is we might
want the transaction history. So, this
is the whole TXO outset instead of the
UTXO outset.
We we definitely want that so we cannot
get that.
We could, but then the size of the
database gets larger because you need to
store all outputs, not just the unspent
ones.
And so, that's the first issue. The
second issue is
how large like so large that we cannot
run on a server
or we can abide that big server for it.
I mean, come on. Like like seriously, if
this is the issue and and we could buy a
server for it. Like I think it would be
worth it because
you know, this is the single most
problematic thing that we have
performance-wise in in Wasabi wallet.
This is why we are not like
like like Blue wallet.
This is This is the reason and and if it
would be feasible
then
I think it would be worth it.
But let me try to summarize the
complexity of why it might still not be
feasible. Yeah, there are other uh-huh.
Exactly, there are others. So one is the
size of the database.
The The other is the number of addresses
that a single client is looking for.
Uh and my client often has over 10,000
used addresses.
Uh and so we would need to query all of
them.
And not just once, but every time you
load the wallet.
And so we have I don't know 10,000 users
with each 10,000 addresses making
queries over the entire blockchain
database, so to say.
That's
that turns very expensive very quick. Uh
and how however a solution around this
is
You will just do only do it once.
Well, next time you open the wallet, you
might have received a coin to one of
those many addresses.
Oh. Oh, yeah. Yeah, right. Uh yes.
So So I think like the other is a couple
kind of layers of So yeah, Max and I
went through this. There There's a
couple layers of kind of mitigation you
can do. So So one layer is you can
you can also just look at which
addresses were because of kind of this
homomorphic encryption thing, because
you can query
kind of arbitrary data as long as the
server kind of
forms it for you. Um
you could have a database that says,
"When were these wallets last interacted
with?"
And you could just query that database,
and you could find out, "Okay, none of
my wallets or you know, 9,000 of these
addresses were not
nothing happened on them in the last
since I last opened this app, right?"
And then for the thousand that are
remaining, you could look and see, you
know, which uh
which ones of them
have a balance still or are still
active, and then you could retrieve each
of their transaction histories kind of
individually.
Um it's not perfect, but something I'll
do is I think I will
I will try to build up a number of
addresses in my wallet that's large
enough to kind of
test with. And I I would love to play
around and and and see
how how this could work or at least
yeah.
Yeah, I I I I think it's a kind of
urgent challenge. So, um
yeah.
And it's it's cool tech, so.
Mhm. Another interest like the the cool
thing is like private information
retrieval from a database is it seems
massively big like as a concept and we
can use it in many different areas. One
for example might be to query the
mempool of someone else.
Which you you boot up your client and
and you have unconfirmed transactions,
and this way you could be able to to get
them.
So, I did that in in hidden wallet. I
was querying the entire mempool of all
the nodes I'm connected to.
But it got got expensive pretty fast.
If you're if you're interested in the in
the in the like checking addresses you
don't own, um I think that's also very
feasible. I don't know if that's
interesting, but um
I think that today your options are
pretty bad. So, I think I think at least
on that front
yeah, we're we're we're we're kind of
clearly better than than
than the best way you have today to to
kind of look up the address of a of a
balance that you don't already
have in your wallet of a of an address.
So, that is a super important point and
that might
Mhm.
So, what what what are people looking in
block explorers? They are looking
looking at uh
quite a few things there.
But,
but building a private block explorer is
based on this protocol might actually be
it possible and and yes, that's a huge
huge huge thing. Like really huge.
Right now people are putting in and
people I mean like I do that as well and
so, we are putting in our our
addresses in block explorers to check if
everything is going well or
how I was constructing the this
transaction.
Stuff like that. And well, that's uh
that's a huge database that block
explorers have.
Um
so, that's
that's pretty problematic. I hope I
it's not going to
be like
that well-known fact that they are going
at
going for block explorers to
to to disclose data, you you know. Yeah,
I mean if I was I would definitely
subpoena a block explorer.
I think I think Ledger keeps keeps their
logs on Ledger Live for like 5 years or
something.
So, yeah, I think I think
Yeah, I don't know if you guys are
I think that's another angle we're
interested in is this hardware wallet
kind of integration. I think it's kind
of funny how you go to kind of you
you're currently able to go to great
lengths and kind of keep all your
private keys on hardware, but then when
you want to just like know how much
money you have, you have kind of have to
you kind of have to just you end up kind
of just going to a block explorer and or
Ledger or whoever and kind of
just telling them your address and your
IP address and stuff. So, yeah.
You could connect it to the your own
node, right? Yes. It's good and stuff,
so yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Hey you guys, especially for
for mobile clients and stuff. Yeah, go
ahead.
You know, even when you connect to your
own node, which is something you brought
up earlier, but the the problem with
this is you still put your sensitive
information on another computer.
And and you sure you're the one mainly
in control of that computer, but maybe
you get hacked or maybe you are already
hacked. And so, the the less information
you store on someone on another
computer, the better. Like an existing
example is Electrum X versus Electrum
personal server.
Electrum personal server stores your
extended public key on the server.
Versus Electrum X only receives an
address and then forgets it later. And
so, if someone walks into your your
house and and takes your Electrum
personal server, he knows your X pub.
Versus if he takes your your Electrum X,
he knows nothing.
So, this is better in in the sense like
I would want to run
a spiral block explorer on top of my own
node just so that if someone gets hold
of my computer, he he still doesn't know
anything.
Yeah, I I think another way to think
about it would be, you know, if you want
to just kind of like
not do the management, but get all the
privacy, I think this is the way to do
it. If you run
Spiral in AWS, you know, like you can be
very confident that they don't learn
anything about what you query,
uh but you also don't have to like
take it with you when you move and
figure out your ISP's like, you know,
static IP situation so you can use it on
your phone when you're going somewhere
or, you know, something like that.
So, yeah.
So,
if I understand it correctly, the reason
why we cannot use it is
because
there are two two problems here.
First,
if we want to have the entire
transaction history of an address, then
we would have to run a server that
might be too big for us.
Uh like there is no such a server
existing in this world to to run that.
And
this question could be investigated,
right?
And the other issue is that
when you have
tens of thousands of addresses,
like
it is taking long
to make those tens of thousands of
of uh
cryptographic key challenge exchanges
to to figure out the entire transaction
history. So, this is this might be
taking like half an hour or or how how
long.
If I may add something, you can have
multiple servers, let's say in Amazon,
and running them in parallel, right?
With spiral on. So,
it should be costly, but still more
fast, I mean.
Yeah, Adam, for your info, this is a CPU
heavier, but it's parallelizable. So, if
you get a server with 50,000 CPU cores,
then it would be super quick.
And you can have multiple of them.
But I don't think that's that's needed,
right? If you can just multiply CPU
cores,
there
Is Is there a speed difference between
having two servers with each five CPU
cores versus one server with 10 CPU
cores?
No, not really. I think I think you'll
run into memory at some point. I mean,
you'll you'll you'll want to you know,
you'll start thinking, "Okay, well, if I
put if you put 5,000 cores on a system
with eight gigs, you might get you might
get bottlenecked by other things." So,
so there is kind of a a thing. I will
say I don't think it's super feasible
It's
you know, CPUs are cheap, but they're
not that cheap. So, I don't want to
I think I I agree with kind of Max's
assessment that
that for this to be feasible, we we need
to find a way to
do this for large numbers of addresses,
and not have it be like,
you know, dollars per lookup, you know,
like like significant amount of money
per lookup. Because I think that's
that's if the goal is to lower the
barrier to entry and to like make it
better, right? That's that's going to be
a a roadblock. It's going to be tough to
to want to pay a dollar every time you
want to know how much money you have,
you know. So, um I I I believe we we can
work on this. I'm not I'm not I I
haven't lost all hope. I think it's
really useful to hear that that people
have so many addresses and I want to
know more about like
what those addresses look like. I you
kind of explained that they're kind of
the outputs of a
of a they're output addresses as a
result of a coin join, sometimes a
failed coin join.
Uh but
um yeah, the more I can kind of
understand that, the more I think if it
would be it it could be feasible kind of
to to
to make progress.
Mhm. Yeah, but I would guess the vast
majority of these addresses are unused.
So, they never made it on the
blockchain.
And then on only a
well, rather smaller number
made it on the blockchain and is already
spent. And so, not in the UTXO set
anymore.
And then the smallest percentage is
going to be the the
the unspent
UTXO addresses.
Okay. Okay.
Lucas,
Certainly, I mean, spent so so something
cool about spent coins is that like, you
know, once they're spent, they can't
kind of come back, right? So,
uh
yeah, we can kind of exploit that. Um
okay.
Lucas, what's your take about all this?
Um
can we
use it uh
somehow if not even if it's uh
can we use
use it to
to make Wasabi
like really light?
Or
or or even should we even if we could
work it out? Like you you are the one
who wrote the long right sphere to
stuff. So, you put a lot of thoughts
into around here.
Uh
Honestly, I don't
I would like to know more about the the
technology, but when I enter into the
the meeting, they were already
discussing things that
I mean, how to how to use the
technology, but not what the technology
really is.
So, I try to do my best to understand.
Basically, what I think is
the technology
is clearly good, right?
So,
I'm sure there are many scenarios that
we can
many problems that we used to have can
be solved by this.
But,
I don't know exactly
how can we use it for our
let's say for reconstructing our local
UTXO set. I mean, the UTXO
that is relevant for the wallet, right?
And all the transactions and all the
information.
I I cannot see it.
Basically, because
the problem that we have is for mainly
for
new users, right? Or users that have to
for some reason to resynchronize the the
the
the wallet, but I use the wallet
more or less
frequently, right? And
it takes nothing for me to to open, to
synchronize. It's just To me, it's it's
exactly the same as Blue Wallet, right?
It's very good. So,
I think it
No, I think it
it doesn't worth the effort.
To
E- even if
it even if the technology
No, no, the technology. Even if the
the requirement of the technology in
terms of bandwidth,
storage, CPU, even if if we can afford
that, I I don't know if we can afford to
to change the architecture of the wallet
to to use this technology, right? And
even if we can afford all of that, I
don't know if the result will be so good
because we have to do a lot of requests,
lots. And and the process of discovering
the wallet is is is the same, right?
I don't know what's the keys. So, I have
to query one key, one key, one key, one
key, one key, and
we will discovering that Oh, well, now I
have to try with the next 21 keys or the
next
I don't know. Some of our users have
minimum gap limit of I don't know.
600. I don't know. So, I have to to
query the next 600
keys. No, I I I
I don't think it it is it is possible.
However, I'm sure
uh
this is something because you know the
PI
PIR
um
technologies have been improving a lot
and now it seems this is like
this is like
something great, a great achievement,
right? Before first time I I I read
something about this,
uh three servers were required for for
this because one server keep one table,
the other server keep a different kind
of information. It was a
really mess, but now it's getting
it seems it's getting
better and better. And
So, we have to have an eye on this
technology, but not for synchronizing
the wallet. I'm pretty sure about it.
I think that's a lot of
sense. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, I I um your
your point about the multiple servers is
is funny. Yeah. I mean, it used to be
that you had to trust that the servers
don't collude,
which is kind of a silly assumption.
Yeah. We've come a long way.
Yeah. Yeah.
I think I I'm really interested in this
in this private block explorer thing,
and I think it it it might not be part
of Wasabi Wallet, but I think it's
obviously part of like an ecosystem of
of private Bitcoin. I mean, if you use
Wasabi Wallet, but then use a public
block explorer,
you're kind of [__] it up, you know?
You're kind of not
you're you're kind of defeating some of
the purpose of the wallet. So, I I I I
hope at least those two things sound
kind of complimentary.
Sorry, yes. I I completely agree. In
fact, many times we say, "Okay, how can
we, for example, provide more
information to the users, right?"
Because basically,
our server
have a global view of the blockchain,
while a client has only a local view of
the of the of the blockchain, right? So,
basically,
the client many times can can take
advantage of of information that only
the server knows, but you cannot ask the
the server, "Hey, can you
Could you please tell me this?" Because,
well,
in that case, you are revealing
information to the server. So, sometimes
you you want to say, "Okay, how can I
ask for this to a central server without
revealing my my identity or my my my
intentions, right?"
that kind of things
um um
is is something that That's why I say
that we have to keep an eye on on on on
on this
on this technology.
Yeah, wait. So, So, that's a great
point. So, so So, I know uh I'm kind of
more familiar I I been in cryptography
but not crypto. So, I'm I'm kind of like
I was really into Bitcoin in like 2015
IT 8 our our class and then I like
totally checked out.
Um that's I Yeah, so I'm a little
unfamiliar but but what kinds of
metadata What kind of like data do block
explorers provide about an address
that
is kind of that global state. So, I can
think of like in in in in the like kind
of Ethereum version, I can think of
like, you know, I don't know, they like,
I don't know, some NFT thing, they like
pull up some image or, you know, there's
like that kind of data, but uh
what are you thinking of
uh that is global that that that these
explorers would show?
Of course Of course we
we don't know, right? It's IP address,
Bitcoin address.
Ah, I see. What
So, what IP submitted this this this
address?
Yep.
Are there um There There's also Is there
like a kind of uh naming? So, is there
like a DNS equivalent like uh
people who use like Opera turn to kind
of store data in some
kind of structured way to to register a
name or whatever?
Um that kind of data is also
while it's in the transaction, the
metadata about it is not, right? Like
Maybe to combine the block explorer with
a lightning explorer, so you would, for
example, see which on-chain transactions
are associated to a certain lightning
node public key.
I see. Yes, so that's information that's
not local normally.
So, today I guess there's almost no
private way to look that up. I guess you
just your best bet is to use tour and to
use a public block explorer
and be careful.
So, um different
but since Lucas brought up that private
information retrieval isn't a new thing,
like
why is Spiral new or or how does it
improve upon what came before?
Sure, it's a great question. So, um
yeah, I mean there's So, private
information retrieval as a problem was
posed yeah, like in the '80s and there's
been like
a bunch of kind of talk about it, but it
never was practical. My best my my
biggest the thing I always make fun of
is like um
I think IBM had like a big demo where
you could look up like the 50 US states
privately and it was like a big demo in
20, you know, I think 2019 or something
uh that the you could look up 50 states.
So, you know, it wasn't like a very
large database. It was like the capitals
of the 50 US states.
Um
the
the reason we've come a long way and
what Spiral does does
what advancement kind of Spiral made was
was basically uh just
it wasn't something super special. It
was it was a lot of it was the
accumulation of a lot of research tricks
that like we kind of knew about but
hadn't implemented or
I just hadn't tried in in the particular
way that we did. Uh I think we are
definitely like
the accumulation of years of research
rather than like some kind of
fundamental like we noticed something
that no one else did. Uh we we we just
brought to bear like a lot of techniques
all at once. Kind of uh very analogously
to how ZK stuff has has grown for in
cryptography, you know, like years of
research from smart people eventually
makes some problems, you know, feasible.
So, yeah.
In particular, what we really did what
we really focused on was making queries
smaller.
So, the a big problem with most previous
schemes that were efficient on the
server side was that then the queries
were like hundreds of megabytes. So, we
we found ways to exploit the fact that,
you know, with fully homomorphic
encryption you can compute any function
on encrypted data.
So, we we kind of you we a crypto
function that expands the query. So, we
can send a very small query and then the
server can do work to expand it into a
vector.
It's pretty cool.
Yeah, okay. And then somewhat related,
but like how does peer review work for
for such a paper cuz it it seems to me
it's not the new cryptography. Just as
you say, applying old concepts, but I
was the peer reviewer
Yeah, so so it's a good question. I
remember my advisor was like, "Yeah, are
we are we is this going to be kind of
like publishable?" And we um
We actually after we had that
conversation, we did come up with some
new cryptography. So, we we did end up
kind of
creating some some new techniques, kind
of constructing a kind of
variation or change to to old schemes.
Um so, we we we did end up publishing it
and and I presented it at Oakland, which
is like the kind of top security
conference for for academics. So, um I
think we were in less of a we were not
in like a theoretical cryptography
venue. We were in like a
privacy-enhancing
technologies kind of venue, but uh
it was still yeah, I mean it was a big
deal
for the reason you pointed out, which is
it hasn't been practical and I think our
work was kind of one of of several works
that took it from being impractical to
practical. There are There are now a
couple, but at the time we were kind of
one of the early ones that
Yeah, I mean, when we told people, you
know, you go to the site and you could
read Wikipedia, that was like a big deal
cuz I think
everything else had been kind of
speculative. It was like, if you were
looking up a sensitive medical condition
in theory, and if you wanted to, you
know, there were a lot of like
hypotheticals.
So, yeah.
Yeah, the MVP demos are pretty great.
Yeah, if you have ideas for other ones,
let me know. I I want to do Ethereum,
and I want to do um
uh sorry, uh the a password checker. So,
I know I don't know if you guys have
seen Have I Been Pwned, but they have
like a site where you where you put in a
password to see if it's been leaked,
but, you know, of course, you're just
giving them your password. They do some
hashing and stuff. They They They say
it's okay, but, you know, you could do
much better with PIR. So.
I think DNS is also something we're
interested in, although there There are
complications there, but uh yeah, DNS is
also exciting.
Sorry, this this is not about the this
this topic, right? But, just
curiosity.
How do you How do you see the
uh how
how
I don't know how to ask. Uh
homomorphic encryption.
How
far do you think we are from a fully I
mean, something that I, for example, can
operate in a in a remote on data
on encrypted data in a remote
I don't know, in for example, I save
something in Google in Google Drive for
example, right? And I can and I come for
example, I don't know, add information
to to
to
to that file, to that encrypted file.
Do you think
Do you think we we will see something
like that?
It's a great question, honestly. Yeah,
it's a great question. I think there's a
lot of companies There's a There's a
surprising number of companies kind of
do this who will tell you like, "Yes." I
I am I take a very
I take a fairly pessimistic stance on
this. I think something companies are
really excited about is encrypted
machine learning. What they really want
to do is do machine learning on
encrypted data.
Which of course is kind of just like a
way of using cryptography to violate
your privacy
instead of using it to What they want to
do is do like machine learning on your
encrypted on your end-to-end encrypted
photos or your end-to-end encrypted you
uh messages. So, it's kind of like
almost like the the evil version.
Um yeah.
I I think the good news is those are
really impractical. I think it's just
like
people in the field know this, but
encrypted machine learning is just like
you can do it if you want, but it's
really expensive and it it'll never be
it'll always be like 100 times more
expensive than doing it the regular way.
So, as the regular way gets more
expensive and people now want to do like
DALL-E and they want to do GPT-3, like
now paying 100 times that cost is is too
hard. We're just barely able to do
private machine learning from like 2010.
So, you know,
I I'm not super optimistic on that
front. I I think something that is
really quite realistic that I'm really
personally excited about, part of why
I'm I'm founding this company, is I
would like to find a way to to kind of
raise money and and fund the building of
metadata private messaging services.
So,
uh it can you the thing I I want to
build is basically like uh WhatsApp or
or any or signal, but uh they don't
learn who you talk to.
So, that is something we can use
homomorphic encryption for and then that
is amazing because
uh obviously who you talk to is really
sensitive.
And if we could hide that data uh even
more than what you say, but also who you
who you talk to,
uh that would be really cool. So, so
that's that's that's something I see as
as as really realistic. And we have to
do this foundational work of making PIR
practical first, but but once we do
that, I think building a messenger I
I I hope I can in 5 years tell you,
"Yeah, like, you know, you can
you can go and then message people and
and uh the service will never learn who
you who you talk to."
So.
It's pretty sweet. Just a fun fact.
But the signal groups
uh use the key verified anonymous
credential cryptography scheme that we
use for our WabiSabi coin joins.
So, it'd be nice if if now we throw your
homomorphic encryption on top and
So, what what is that called? Is it it's
it's a key What is key?
Key verified anonymous credentials.
Ah, okay.
This is for a context or or for for
setup of the conversation?
We use it as as basically e-cash token
for access rights.
Okay. So, the the token gets created on
during input registration and you can
only register an output if you present
such a token.
And it's it's anonymous e-cash, so to
say.
Very rough explanation.
Cool. Are are you familiar with the
Chaumian blind signatures?
Chaumian blind signatures? Yes. Uh I'm
familiar with the name Chaumian, but I
know I haven't heard of uh
Chaumian blind signatures. Uh, blind
signatures
probably did a piece that about that,
but I did I could not off the top of my
head say what say what exactly it is.
It's for voting, right?
I think.
Yeah, so key-verified anonymous
credentials are a generalization of the
blind signatures.
In Wasabi Wallet 1.0, we used blind
signatures. In 2.0, we used key-verified
anonymous credentials.
Oh, so this is actually a homomorphism,
too. It's It's actually Yeah, so if you
want to think of it
If you want to think of it this way, I
mean, uh you're exploiting a
These signatures also exploit a a
homomorphism in RSA. Uh, they're just
It's just a different homomorphism. Um
Yeah, so homomorphic encryption is is a
little bit of If you want to think of it
this way, you could think of it as a
generalization of of
Uh, it's it's it's also a generalization
of of pairing-based cryptography, if
you've seen that before. There's kind of
like that's a very specific homomorphism
for ECC, but
yeah.
Yeah, they're they're connected.
As As far as I remember, we we do use uh
Peterson commitments or or generally
speaking homomorphic encryption for the
amount of the value of of these
credentials.
Ah, okay.
Yes.
Yeah, so those are again, yeah,
homomorphic, right? Uh, sorry, go ahead.
Yes, because we have to to uh the server
needs to verify that the operation that
we realized
with the amounts
um
are correct without knowing the amounts
itself itself, so
Yes.
But it's something I mean, I I I don't
know what uh
I don't know exactly how to define
homomorphic encryption, right?
Um because homomorphic encryption
like
And the concept is it's it's it's it's
okay, but
it it it sounds like something that is
not
still possible, right? So it's
Yeah.
homomorphic
homomorphic encryption Yeah, and the
scope is this for
most of the time it's something like
what we what we do is
basically or we operate in a
in a
in a Yes, in a
pedersen commit committed
value and that value is basically
a point in an elliptic curve and that's
it.
It's It's funny. I I think elliptic
curves are way more complicated. I'm
always I'm always like I think
lattice-based cryptography and
homomorphic stuff, which is which is
lattice-based and you know, was
initially pioneered for post-quantum
resistance and stuff. I think it's way
easier to understand than elliptic
curves cuz like, you know, what is an
elliptic curve really? You know, I'm
always like very confused not confused,
but it it's always very abstract for me.
Whereas
lattices are just, you know, it's
matrices and it's noise and I understand
that a lot better. It's like a lot
easier for me. So it's it's funny. You
should You guys are It's a real crypto
people if you guys are just sitting
around thinking about Pedersen
commitments and homomorphic
zones and
I I I I promise homomorphic encryption
is is
it's also is in some ways much easier to
understand. So, yeah.
Uh we we are not crypto cryptographers
here. I mean, we we are but
yes,
we have to
like a duck and talks like a duck. I
don't know. You guys are You guys are as
much cryptographers as
as as anyone, I think. Zach Zach's full
cryptographers.
The most dangerous kind.
Yes. Yes. It's true. I I suppose
academic cryptographers are less
dangerous, you know. I think we mostly
write papers and then that's it.
So, to be fair, we hired a cryptographer
uh for for for for this. So,
so that's okay. But, he's not here.
Yep. Plus, we we didn't roll our own
crypto, but we're script kiddies and and
just copied it from an existing paper.
So, should be all right.
Well, that's what a cryptographer would
do, right? That's That's exactly they
would say, "We're not going to roll our
own. We're going to get a library,
right?" So, you did the right thing.
we kind of did roll, right? Like, we
wrote a lot of cryptographical
Yep. Did not use a library. But, the
concept we didn't roll.
Lucas, would you say we rolled our own
crypto or not?
Good question. I
No. I mean, the crypto that we are using
is just a an a very
specific case of the one more general
case that is the one that uh described
the signal
the
the signal white paper for for anonymous
groups.
So, they have a general case, and we use
only one specific case of that. So, we
we are not doing that. Now, the problem
is in the in the in implementation. I
mean, the code. Someone has to write the
code, right?
Uh and and that is where
developers always make mistakes, huge
mistakes.
Um
but so yes, we implemented that because
there are no libraries for that. There
is no
It's not I mean
it's So, basically
let's say we
implemented our own crypto library,
right?
Um however, the good part is that
in my case at least, I made so many
mistakes before
that I think I I learned by doing and by
making mistakes
and and and also the code is extremely
reviewed and
Uh
so
I think we did it really really well
this time.
Sommeli, do you still have time? Are are
we just boring you at this point?
I have about uh 10 or 15 more minutes if
you guys want to keep chatting. Cool.
Well, most important questions first.
Guys, what do you have for Sommeli for
the next 15?
So, how about a big one?
Um
All right. Go ahead, Sommeli.
You have to bring a big one now.
Sorry. Sorry about that. Uh this is
one question that I've been
meaning to ask. Is that um given that
uh the homomorphic encryption has
addition and multiplication,
as far as I know
about abstract algebra, does that enable
uh
um Turing complete machines or
computations? Yep. Yep. Yeah, that's
that's what the sometimes you see this
abbreviated as fully homomorphic
encryption. That's what the fully means.
So, yeah, you can do arbitrary
competition encrypted. Anything you can
compute on on regular data, it's
possible to compute on encrypted data.
Yeah.
I see. So, so you can uh
uh
in a hypothetical scenario, how how does
one implement for say, you know, in
Boolean logic, they say the NAND
gate is
yeah, it's a good question. Yeah.
Uh how does that going to translate into
homomorphic operations? Yeah, so um
there are some at homomorphic schemes
that actually operate directly on the
bit level. So, so they actually
implement a NAND gate uh in the scheme
basically. In fact, the scheme basically
just
is a way to compute a homomorphic NAND
gate, and then everything else just goes
from there. Um
something to know, I guess, about the
fully part of fully homomorphic
encryption, something we didn't we kind
of mentioned, but uh
the the homomorphic encryption that
Spiral uses is bounded depth. What that
means is like there's a certain depth of
the computation of the circuit that you
can compute.
Uh and then after that, it doesn't work.
Uh so, um
that that kind of bounded depthness is
is not fully homomorphic, right? You
can't do anything Turing complete in in
bounded depth. So, there is a kind of
encryption a homomorphic encryption that
can do arbitrary
arbitrarily large and arbitrary
computation. So, so that is that is
fully homomorphic encryption. Um and it
exists. We don't We don't use that that
part of it
because it's uh quite slow.
But, uh it does exist. It is possible. I
I don't suppose you can make uh uh
a mini computer out of a fully
homomorphic encryption.
Oh, yeah, you absolutely can. In fact,
uh people are working on it for for for
roll-ups and stuff. Yeah, it's it's
possible. Yeah.
Uh if I may ask Fabricio, is is that
implementable in lookup tables and you
know, um FPGAs and stuff?
Yeah, it's not impossible to hardware
acceleration.
You you preceded me was the was the
question I was was going to ask if the
implementation on ASICs is could
constitute a
a a significant improvement on
on
question. Yeah. So so we've we've we've
actually tried GPUs and GPUs are are
really well suited for this. Um
Nvidia actually has like an instruction
set extension and a library that they
they put out that that helps you do
this. So it's not uh I think they might
have Yeah, I don't know what the status
of it is, but they are thinking about
this. Um
ASICs and FPGAs are kind of not very
useful cuz you need a what what you need
is you need a fairly significant amount
of memory cuz the database needs to fit
in memory and GPUs have a lot of effort
invested in really really good memory
access, right? So actually GPUs are kind
of optimal.
Um we we we tried it it
at the time GPUs were really expensive.
So we actually it didn't become cost
effective. It was it was cool and it was
it was fast, but it wasn't very cost
effective. Now
now that GPUs are way cheaper, it it
might be.
I have to I have to like revisit it, but
yeah.
Yeah. I I I actually a question because
you just said the database has to be
kept in memory. Uh is that the case in
Spiral? Yes.
Okay, but then I mean if we have a large
data
data set with for example the full
blockchain, you know, many hundreds of
gigabytes.
Right.
All of that needs to be in memory?
Yeah. Yeah, it does. I I I will say the
memory cost usually kind of pales in in
terms of in in comparison to the compute
cost. So, I mean making everything fit
in memory is
I mean hundreds of gigs of mem- memory
is like on a cloud provider
not that expensive actually. And once
once you have some everything fitting in
memory, I mean you can throw as many
compute cores as you want at it. So,
it's it's yeah, it's a limit, but it's
not
Yeah, it's not crazy.
Out of topic question for Fabricio.
Um
Um I've been quite interested in FPGA
development. What's this Have you looked
into the um
uh open source um
hardwares uh Verilog synthesis stuff
like um
IceStorm or something? Uh sorry, um
project
starts with letter S. I forgot.
Um
but actually these are crypto project
regarding FPGA cuz actually I'm dealing
with FPGA for
uh actually for genomic recognition.
Uh
but um
actually regarding crypto I I actually I
didn't look
uh
yet, let's say.
But uh
actually uh
if you
let's say regarding for example the the
the primitive function uh to for example
do
do hashing stuff or
uh
cryptographic primitives um
I think you you can improve
probably one order of magnitude if you
if you implement some
some crypto cryptographic computation
and and hashing on on on FPGAs. This is
something that I think is a
is
uh
worth looking at.
Definitely.
Cool. Um
last question for you. Um
has it been uh feasible um given that uh
is it been you know in uh FPGAs you are
bound with like a manufacturer's
um
you know tooling
and lately there has been some
developments regarding open source um
um tooling for like Yosys and stuff. Uh
have you used those tools before or is
it still vendor locked?
Uh
well, at the moment we we are using
proper proprietary tools.
Uh for example uh Vivado, no? Which is a
very
uh
very one very famous.
But actually uh
no, actually didn't yet look at at the
let's say open source
uh
open source development regarding that.
I will have a look.
For sure. Oh cool.
Thank you so much. Thank you so much.
Awesome.
Thank you very much for for coming here.
That was really kind of you.
Yeah, thanks so much for I I I learned
so much. I'm I'm learning so much about
what what Bitcoin people want and need
and stuff. And you guys are super
helpful. So thank you so much. I I want
to The only thing I want to say is, you
know, let's let's keep in touch,
especially as we get closer to building
something that looks
less like just a balance checker and
more like a private block explorer. I
would love to see if if there's kind of
a
synergy between what we offer. I I love
to see if like people who use Wasabi
Wallet also want to like use a private
block explorer. So, um yeah, if that
sounds good, I would I would love to
keep in touch.
Mhm. Yeah, definitely. I mean,
especially if if if if you run the
server and we don't have to and we can
use it for Absolutely, yeah. Yeah, yeah.
You know, we we can use it for small
niche things like finding out the amount
of the the input of a payment
transaction so that we can keep on bit.
You know, these types of small things
where it doesn't really make sense for
us to
make huge infrastructure changes for
those very very niche case things.
No, we we'd love to we'd love to mostly
we'd love to see people use the server.
We'd love to see like what your pain
points are. We're we're absolutely happy
to host and run those kinds of things.
So, yeah, absolutely.
That's pretty sweet. And I'm yeah,
really curious what we can come up with
to use this other than
just just blockchain sync and and and
wallet balance sync.
Yeah. Yeah.
Pretty cool.
Yeah, Zsolt, just one comment. You you
know, it's not obvious what
we can do with this technology. I I
don't know if everybody understand. In
fact,
I think the the the white paper is not a
good starting point for. In fact, it's
Yeah. You know, so
uh so
it sometimes
uh
you need to know the tools that you have
available. So,
when when you say, "Okay, we can fix the
all there is this technology that we can
use and this is exactly for this." So,
Right. Right. if you have documentation
or or presentations or examples or
snippets or whatever or use cases or
right?
That's
that's also cool. I I'm pretty
interesting on on
this stuff. I will definitely send you
guys
that stuff. You're totally right. You
have to kind of know what the tool is
before you can really see where it where
it makes sense to use. Absolutely.
Okay, thank you guys.
Yeah, then I guess that's that's it for
the recorded part of of this week's
Wasabi Research Club. Thanks for all the
guests joining us here and all the
viewers online.
Hopefully, this was as exciting and
useful for you guys as it was for me.
Again, thanks Sumair for for coming
here.
Real pleasure, real honor. Let's stay in
touch. Yeah, absolutely. Thank you so
much.
See you on the next show. Bye-bye. Yeah,
see you. Bye.